foreign
[Music]
hello everybody
it is that time of the week again it's
ask a budget time
so welcome to episode 53 of ask abidjit
uh to all the returning viewers it's
great to see you all thank you for
returning to the new viewers welcome to
the ask a budget show so let's see who
all we have with us let us see
i can see ashi ashwarya aditya
divya raj
lover of military and capitalism bhai
chi ching
om
aaron joy deep
vinit banu prakash kalyan ricky
aniruddha
she
[Music]
and so many more people
i am unable to greet you all but thank
you for being here it's great to be back
with you all
so what shall we discuss today okay
before we get into the discussions
before we get into the questions
a couple of things uh i have started a
discord server many of you have been
asking for a few months for several
months
for me to start a discord server so i
have started a discord server the invite
link
is pinned on top of the chat please join
it's a place where you can
all get together and discuss various
matters or the kind of things that we
discuss on this channel
so you can all get together form a
community
share information knowledge views news
and all that have discussions have
debates
and
you know
learn new things
so that's the discord server i hope that
you all join
uh secondly a few people not a few
people many people have been asking me
about the about the super chats why
don't i have super chats on this channel
i think i i had uh spoken about this a
few months ago but i think lots of new
people have joined so they're not aware
of it so i had
kept super chats on in the very
beginning of of the ask a budget show
maybe the first few episodes but then i
decided to switch them off because it
was creating this divide between the
people who
who could pay and
who could not pay i mean most of the
viewers on this channel are students
they're teenagers the youngsters
and
i think it's just inappropriate for me
to answer questions in exchange for
money
uh i don't care what other channels are
doing i think it's just wrong i don't
want to do it
i'm not doing this for money i'm just
doing this to to have a conversation
with you all and and to you know discuss
things so that is why i'm doing it i'm
not doing this thing to earn money from
answering questions that's that's just
obscene in my opinion so that's the
reason why i have switched off the super
chats no super chats on this channel
especially when i'm taking questions uh
in case some of you want to contribute
you can
contribute in some way you can become
members so
thank you to all of you who have joined
as members welcome to the new members
thank you very much and there are some
other options if you want to contribute
right so you can use that button there
will be no super chats on the channel
everybody will be treated equally
knowledge must always be free there
should be no restrictions
uh so yeah so thank you to all the new
members thank you to all those who of
you who have contributed to this channel
thank you very much i really appreciate
it
uh
and one more thing people have been
asking me is what happened to the short
clips
so in the last three four months i have
uploaded i think about 500 short clips
of individual answers
on this channel
so that phase is done now i am not going
to upload any more short clips all the
answers that i have given on this
channel hundreds of answers they're all
available you can search if you have any
specific question you're looking for you
can just go use the search functionality
and you will be able to find the episode
in which i have answered the question
the timestamps are all there mostly so
you can
find those answers i still have enough
material to upload another thousand
short clips but i will not be doing that
anymore now the focus of this channel is
going to change i'm going to create long
form content documentary style content
coming very soon
so there will be no more short clips
coming up on this channel
right i think that that takes care of
those questions now let us see what
questions you have
what would you like me to talk about
let's see what questions you all are
asking
uh
okay let's take some questions there are
lots already that's wonderful that's
wonderful
um
kostov asks is it true or myth that the
grandfather of jawaharlal nehru the real
name was
ghazi and he was a soldier in the in the
army of baadusa zafar
so that's the
that's the story one hears all the time
but is it documented is there any
documentary evidence for this we don't
know
this is a this is a story a rumor i
don't know what it is but it's it simply
refuses to go away
so maybe there could be some truth to it
but has it been proven does the evidence
exist do the records exist of such a
person having served under the mughal
empire as whatever as a soldier or the
kothwal of delhi or whatever they say
i don't know i haven't investigated this
but yes i've heard the story
i've heard the claims these very strong
claims that this is the story but you
know i haven't investigated it myself
and i am not sure if anybody has
produced
any actual documentation or actual
records from that time that
proved this
conclusively so i i personally don't
know for sure but yes i've certainly
heard of this this story
okay let's take some more questions
okay
it was chaos on the first day and i
think you're talking about the first
episode of azkaban you know when you
start something new when you start a new
show a new program
you're doing it on a trial and error
basis you don't know how it's going to
go unless until you actually do it so
yeah it took me two three episodes to
realize what is working what's not
working what i want what i don't want
so yeah then i started figuring out how
things go
and things were much smoother later on
uh initially i was taking everything
from the chats initially the super chats
were turned on so i think that was not a
good choice so then i switched the chats
off super chat's off and then for a very
long time i was taking questions from
the comments you know selected questions
from the comments
so that
uh
that basically uh helped me allow me to
answer very specific questions not
random questions that come from the
chats but that was less interactive it
was certainly i was asking i was
answering all the questions you all were
asking but it was not that interactive
it was all questions that i picked up
because i found them interesting and i
was answering them live
now what i'm doing is i'm doing it fully
interactive uh two sessions per week one
is all from the chat so i'm answering in
real time whatever you are asking in
real time from the chats
and the other session is live video chat
which is even more interactive so now i
think after i have answered like maybe
more than a thousand questions already i
want to make it a little more
interactive so that i get to know all of
you and we we have an actual
conversation you know
so it it keeps evolving you have to keep
evolving adapting
you do things initially on a trial and
error basis but you have to learn
quickly and you have to adapt so i think
that's how this channel has evolved in
the last
four four plus months
since i started the ask a widget show
all right let's take some more questions
dhruv mishra says what is the way to
become a leader in the country of the
country in this kind of electoral system
even though one has capabilities you
know to become a leader in this country
you need to be politically adept you
need to know how to navigate the
dirty murky world of politics
it's not about how great you are how
capable you are how patriotic you are
it's about learning to deal and to
navigate the political system because
that's the only way you are going to
succeed in the political system if you
get elected and to get elected you need
to be a member of a political party and
you need to you know make the right
moves because you will never get you
don't stand any chance of getting
elected
as an independent candidate because all
the political parties their candidates
have almost unlimited financial support
from the political parties i mean on
every election every candidate even at
the lowest levels mla levels they spend
crores of rupees on various
various promotional activities you know
on the election campaign uh
and
a non-political party person doesn't
stand a chance doesn't have any kind of
doesn't have anything close to that sort
of money so you need to become a member
of a political party you need to make
the right moves
and you need to be able to muster uh
support on the ground and so on and so
forth so it's a long involved process
you will find that typically when
somebody gets elected to the highest
position in the country positions in the
country whether it's chief minister or
prime minister there usually pass 50
almost past 60 70 sometimes
because it takes a long time in the
system to rise to that level you have to
to fight your way all the way up you
know from the very bottom
so it's it's
it's quite hard i mean you know the
thing is that
to a certain extent it is important that
somebody who aspires to leadership
should demonstrate the ability to
persevere over a long period of time
and to to fight off all kinds of
challenges and difficulties so it is
actually
it does make sense
for somebody to demonstrate the ability
the capability the perseverance the
willingness the discipline the willpower
to
focus on the goal
for an extended period of time at least
10 years only then i think a person
should be allowed to rise to the highest
positions of power in the country the
leadership positions right
so that is one thing that is actually
desirable but on the other hand there is
so much politics i mean politics is
dirty and murky 95 98 of politicians
don't really care about the country they
are all concerned about their own
personal interests that's something you
see across the world throughout the
world not only in india so yeah you have
to learn to navigate all that if you
want to rise to the top of the country
and become a leader either as a chief
minister or a prime minister someday or
whatever you know
so yeah it's a long learning process
it's a long involved drawn out process
you have to invest your entire life into
it if you want to make a difference
right let's see some more questions
this is an interesting question by
dongre why did the senate of carthage
betray hannibal during the punic wars by
cutting off supplies it's a very
interesting question so the punic wars
took place i think in the second and
first centuries bce it was between the
uh the kingdom of carthage in north
africa present day algeria morocco that
region
uh between the kingdom of carthage in
north africa and the roman empire
and carthage was a very powerful very
prosperous kingdom empire at the time
and there was this uh
this long drawn out
conflict between the two for supremacy
in the mediterranean region
so hannibal was the greatest general
of carthage during the first punic war i
think the first war between these two
empires
and before hannibal his father hamilkar
barka was also one of the greatest
generals of
of the carthaginian empire and he too
was betrayed by the senate
the senate of carthage expected hannibal
and before him his father they expected
these great generals to fight on their
behalf and to defeat the romans but they
were unwilling to support them to the
fullest extent they were unwilling to
give them the supplies the the the arms
ammunition etc that they needed
but they expected them to go and fight
and win
and that happened with hannibal's father
that also happened with hannibal himself
and it eventually led to the defeat of
hannibal in the fight
and the defeat in the death of animal
eventually in the i think in the era of
the first punic war
or the first punic war was not a
complete disaster for carthage it was
kind of a stalemate the romans did win
back some territory from carthage
in the first punic war eventually
and later on in the second punic war it
was total annihilation for carthage
so this is what happens when you have
short-sighted politicians
who are more concerned with their own
personal gain and they are not concerned
with the long-term security prosperity
and future of the country and its people
so it's a very interesting chapter of
history
uh the guy who who spent his entire life
fighting for his kingdom for his country
for the people he served for his nation
he was betrayed by his politicians and
it led to the eventual disastrous
defeat and complete annihilation of
carthage so it's an instructive lesson
from history it is because of
short-sightedness selfishness and
pettiness of these politicians that this
happened
okay let's take more questions
okay chuching dingle asks what was
happening in nagaland during the time of
the mauryan empire that's a very
interesting question so
it's not just about nagaland see we we
tend to think of geographical regions in
the context of today's political
boundaries
so people ask what was happening in
maharashtra 3000 years ago or what was
happening in tamil nadu three thousand
years ago or what was happening in
nagaland or manipur or tripura 2000
years ago and so on
in those days there was no maharashtra
there was no tamil nadu there was
right during the mauryan empire you had
a large
political entity
called the indian civilization it was
all under one emperor during the modern
times now i am not sure if
present-day northeast india was at the
time administered by the
by the mauryan empire
i'm not completely sure that it was
it was certainly very much a part of the
indian subcontinent of the overall
extended indian civilization which
extended all the way to the philippines
uh
but i am not one of the problem is this
our historians have completely totally
neglected the history and the culture of
northeastern india
i mean i i am very acutely aware of the
fact that the people of northeast india
feel neglected they feel like the
government of india treats them like
second-class citizens and there is a
great deal of truth to it
since independence the northeast of
india has been totally neglected there
will be no infrastructure development no
development of any kind it has been left
to its devices and it's
it has undergone
a great deal of strife
and and all of that has been
artificially engineered and so on and
there has been absolutely no historical
research done
in the history of this region you ask
any historian this question they will
have no answer because they have done no
research and if you look at
this region you have a few universities
there
in northeastern india and you have
departments of history there what are
those professors of history doing there
they are doing absolutely nothing they
are teaching from the textbooks but they
are doing no actual original research
they are not asking themselves the
simple questions of what is the history
of this place
whether it is nagaland whether it is
manipur whether it is any other part of
india of of northeastern india there is
no research being done there
and therefore i am unable to answer your
question
if i was in charge of a history
department there
i would take certain specific actions to
uncover the history over time
of let's say nagaland or manipur or
tripura or meghalaya or mizoram or
whatever right
and so on
it's simply not been done in the past 70
years and therefore i don't know i'm
unable to answer this question i mean we
don't even have a chronological history
of the kings of nagaland
what i do know is that we had there was
this big uh
empire kingdom of manipur
which did administer large areas in this
region i think what is now known as
nagaland did come under the jurisdiction
of the kings of manipur for a very long
period of time repeatedly during various
kingdoms
some of the kings of manipur were very
very uh active very dynamic they forged
great territorial uh
jurisdictions some of them even
conquered parts of burma
some of them even captured rangoon and
so on so i think
significant portions of nagaland would
have been under the jurisdiction of the
manipuri kings from time to time
but what is the specific history of this
region what i do know is that the
various so-called tribes of nagaland
they are linguistically very diverse
culturally also very diverse
they all have different languages many
of the tribes can't even speak
or understand each other's language so
there is this new language that has been
constructed naga means you know
which serves as a kind of common
unifying language for this region but
each of these tribes or clans would have
their own
history which has been erased in the
past 100 years or so
the local culture has been destroyed
and a foreign culture has been
transposed on top of it so i don't want
to get into that controversy but the
thing is that there has been no research
done in the history of either nagaland
or even manipur or any part of
northeastern india and that is a crying
shame
india's historians need to be ashamed of
themselves they need to hang their heads
in shame
and the people of india need to call
these historians out and expose them for
their
their election of their duty
so i hope
that research is done because clearly
all of these different tribes and clans
in nagaland and so on have very ancient
histories very old histories that go
back
possibly several thousand years
right so this needs to be
researched these stories need to be
uncovered
and publicized and published you know
these need to be documented
so i hope that happens you know
i hope that the local historians the
professors of history in the local
universities
i think somebody needs to give them a
kick of their backside and make them do
their work which they are paid for
so that's what i can answer but thank
you it's it's great to hear a question
from
from nagaland switching thank you
all right let's see some more questions
i have answered many of these questions
which i'm seeing here already
so in case i am not answering a specific
question that you are asking me go
through my channel i have answered many
of the questions for instance king
vikramaditya i have answered this at
least a couple of times in the past
check it out
okay mohan sinha says there is clear
evidence that the harappan people ate
cow meat
that means it is clear that it is
totally different from vedic culture
okay jagmon i so that's what you are
stating there is clear evidence
that harappan people ate cow meat so
what is this clear evidence have you
provided the clear evidence let me tell
you i i see i'm not criticizing you uh
let me tell you what you mean i know
what you mean so there has been a
research paper published in one of
whether it was nature or somewhere else
in which some researchers analyzed the
contents of a
jar or a pot
in which they found a residue
that is indicative of animal fat
lipids and most specifically uh i think
they identified it as belonging to an
animal of the bovine of one of the
bovine species either a buffalo or a cow
or it's basically fat from cattle and on
the basis of this of the analysis of one
or two i think one jar i think
they have reached the conclusion that
the people of the harappan region ate
cow meat
did the my question is very simple did
they find traces of animal protein
because you know what cow fat
is also found in ghee
incurred
in milk
these lipids are found in the milk
of cows of buffaloes of bovine animals
of all cattle
if you boil milk
in
or in in any kind of vessel and if you
leave it there it's going to
evaporate over time is going to solidify
and the residue which is left behind
will have the same characteristics
as the fat of the animal
so this does not constitute any kind of
clear evidence that the people of
harappa ate comedy and even if you find
evidence in one jar in one place
of let's say hypothetically that
there is incontrovertible evidence that
there was cow meat or or cattle meat in
one jar does it indicate that the same
thing was was was the same uh practice
was prevalent throughout the sindhu
region which is bigger than egypt and
mesopotamia and the middle east put
together
on the basis of even even if you find
one
incontrovertible data point
can you extrapolate that to cover the
entire subcontinent-sized
geographical region
it is absolute stupidity
to do that i am not saying jagman you're
stupid i am saying that if if the
researchers have made such a claim they
are stupid
and they need to be called out for that
point number one is it is evidence of
animal fat it's not evidence of animal
meat right
and secondly they found this they have
claimed to find this the to have found
this i think it is in the saurashtra
region
in gujarat
in one place
so if you find something in one place
does it mean it was practiced everywhere
throughout the sunday region throughout
the uh region of the uh
saraswati civilization which extends
from northern maharashtra all the way to
southern afghanistan and from western up
all the way to balochistan
it makes no sense
so there is no clear evidence that any
such thing happened they found evidence
of animal fat in one place in one jar
in one location
it is not evidence of animal meat it's
just fat it could come from milk it
could come from something else we don't
know what it indicates so this is the
problem this is the problem that you see
throughout these academics they are
intellectually dishonest they are
purposefully misleading the people they
have an agenda a socio-political agenda
they have a hindu-phobic agenda they
want to make people in india believe
that
the aryan invasion thing happened that
the people of the harappan region were
not vedic they were not hindus they
followed some pre-hindu culture they
were cow eaters cow cow cow killers
and so on and so forth
despite all the evidence that is tearing
us in the face they are cherry picking
one or two data points and trying to
construct narratives out of that you
will see this again and again and again
and again
and unfortunately science
is just hard evidence
and
this is they are not going to be able to
succeed because as we uncover more
evidence the patterns become very clear
they are already very clear
that uh
that the harappan people are the
ancestors of all indians today all of us
see those thus far we have um done the
genetic analysis of one individual of
only one individual in the harappan
region we need to start doing that for
more ancient harappan remains so that is
something that needs to happen only when
we examine
several dozen
ancient remains of the harappan
sindhu people
then we will be able to find to to
make better uh
to reach better conclusions
but all the data that we have as of
today
very copious voluminous data from
genetics from linguistics from
population genetics from genomics
linguistics literature archaeology uh
what else do we have geology
hydrology hydro morphology and so much
more all of it points in just one
direction
that
the aryan invasion did happen but the
origin of the iron invasion was india
and it went westwards into europe from
here
and the indo-european homeland the
homeland of the indo-european languages
and culture and religion is india
that is the evidence that is the
pattern that you see throughout all of
these pieces of evidence from these
different disciplines
so this fake narrative they will try and
keep on misleading people all these uh
outlets the wire the print the quint the
squint whatever else they will keep on
publishing reams of misinformation
but eventually
it will be exposed as all lies
okay there have been people publishing
books you know very these books have
been very successful
now let me give you an example tony
joseph's book
uh ancient indians or whatever the hell
it is called
it is absolute garbage but it has so
many good reviews on amazon and very
good sales so
the problem is the education system is
is
has made the people of india susceptible
to this sort of misinformation and
misleading
so but it can't go on forever
because the evidence
is just hard fit facts and hard data
and
the facts are the facts the truth is the
truth the truth is that india is the
original homeland of the indo-european
languages culture people and religion
that's all it is
mudit says can you please speak about
excavation sites in tamil nadu like
hillary yes there have been many
there are several archaeological
uh projects going on in places like key
lady aadhi challange
i'm not sure what the name is and in
many other places why guy
there's a bunch of archaeological sites
that are currently being excavated
and we are finding very interesting uh
pieces of evidence from there so right
now we are in the very early days of
excavation and the media again is is
trying to portray it in various ways so
they're saying there is a new
civilization in killer d there is a new
civilization in adi chalanura this is a
tamil civilization apparently
so again they are trying to portray
every new archaeological site as a
separate civilization
the fact is that everything is part of
one civilization we are finding the same
patterns everywhere
right
uh and now when they find evidence of
the brahmi script they say it is not
brahmay it is tamil brahmi it is
separate from regular brahmi and maybe
tamil brahma is the origin of all
brahmil brahmi scripts and so on
so even when you find this evidence that
conclusively links
these ancient sites in southern india in
tamil nadu to
sites in archaeological sites in
northern india all the way up to
afghanistan with the brahma's crypt they
are trying to still
portray it as something different
so i would say that right now let the
excavations happen
it needs to
continue happening
and i hope that they document all the
evidence properly i hope they construct
museums there in which you can house all
these artifacts
safely
and all the evidence will speak for
itself the the fact is that ancient
india see today if you look at india
india is one
vast interconnected
geographical region it's one nation
today it's not one civilization anymore
it's just a nation state now but from
north to south east to west it is just
one political entity it is it is a vast
region it is all interconnected
so the fact the truth is that even two
thousand two and a half thousand years
ago even five thousand years ago it was
the same situation north south east west
it was all interconnected you will find
the same patterns everywhere you will
find the same culture everywhere you
will find the same cultural artifacts
everywhere you will find the same
scripts everywhere which we are finding
in southern india brahmi but they are
portraying it as tamil brahmi apparently
so these attempts to
to misinform people
are going to continue there's a lot of
politics involved
there are attempts to fabricate evidence
i heard there was some christian pastor
or somebody who had manufactured
fake evidence and he was portraying it
as something else and
all that's what i read in the news
and so on so this is going to go on
unfortunately history has been very
deeply politicized in india it is all
part of a big social engineering project
to destroy indian culture and transpose
foreign culture into
the indian society so it's going to keep
on going i hope that the government does
the right things and
allows the true history to be revealed
without any political interference from
any side you know
just let the facts be revealed whatever
they are whatever they are
the truth needs to come out that's all
all right let's see some more questions
aryan john says what is the difference
between a terrorist and a rebellion what
are my thoughts on the balochistan
liberation army
as a terrorist group by the u.s and
european union
so it all depends on how you want to
portray it
uh
terrorists and rebellions right so
terrorists typically what they do is
that they try to uh
they don't actually fight a proper war
they fight guerrilla warfare and they
stay hidden and they try to
inflict casualties on the civilian
population the non-combatant population
in the hope of terrorizing the common
people
and of destroying their way of life
so the typical uh
tools of the trade are bomb blasts car
bombs train bombs and so on
which go to the very heart of the
lifestyle of the people so it makes
people terrified of ever going outside
in public again of getting on a plane or
a train or a car or going out in public
into a market because these are the
things that are typically targeted by
terrorists so terrorists typically
target the civilians
the non-combatants men women children
the innocent people
that is terrorism a rebellion is a
different thing
a rebellion can be justifiable it can
have you can have just causes for
violence in rebellion
terrorism can never be justified because
they target innocent men women and
children a rebellion can be fought
against an armed force against an
occupying force
for instance uh the 1857 war of
independence was portrayed as a mutiny
rebellion etc it was a just war for the
freedom for the liberation of india from
the foreign occupier
so you can call it a rebellion you can
call it a war whatever but that
that had clear justification it was
morally
correct
so rebels a rebellion can be against an
occupying force
or against a
regime that is unjust unfair and brutal
as long as it targets
the organs of the state
and the the armed forces of the state
then it is a rebellion the moment it
starts targeting civilians it is
terrorism and it has to be crushed and
defeated right now the balochistan
liberation army are they killing
civilians i don't think so
they are trying to fight the occupying
pakistani armed forces
and they are targeting the chinese who
are in who have infiltrated into
balochistan and who are now trying to
uh steal the resources of balochistan i
think that is perfectly justified
right
uh
balochistan was supposed to be a free
state a free country pakistan illegally
invaded and annexed it
in the in the late 1940s right and the
peop the will of the people was crushed
the people have been brutalized
oppressed i mean the atrocities that
have been perfect perpetrated by the
pakistani army and the establishment are
just horrific
and now pakistan has become a chinese
colony de facto chinese colony and the
chinese are targeting balochistan for
all of its resources so they want to
extract all the resource of resources of
balochistan but rajasthan is a very
resource rich region
and all of these resources are have
until now been extracted by pakistan
and now they're the chinese are involved
in this so the balochistan liberation
army is fighting for the freedom of
balochistan and its people from these
occupying powers they are not killing
men women children they are not killing
civilians they are fighting the
occupying pakistani army and the chinese
occupiers
so that is the difference
between terrorists and
genuine rebels the balochistan
liberation army is not a terrorist
organization they are fighting for the
freedom of their land
now the pakistanis and chinese and
whoever else will want to portray them
as
terrorists because it doesn't suit their
agenda right
so they will
they will further their agenda by
portraying them as terrorists
and i'm not sure about the european
union and the u.s if they have also
portrayed the blas terrorists
but at least the pakistanis call them
terrorists and we know why but they are
not really terrorists because they don't
target civilians very simple
utkar says isn't so one of the most
underrated heroes considering he devoted
himself so much to the motherland's
protection absolutely yes i agree skanda
gupta was one of the gupta emperors in
the first millennium
a.d
he
fought off the initial
hunnic invasions of india the shweta
hunas the white horns the hephthalites
had invaded india from the north
and skandagupta devoted his life to to
fighting off these invasions by these
nomadic uh peoples
he i think he uh made this public uh
promise to his people
that i will not sleep on a bed and i
will not eat on a plate
as long as my country is under invasion
i will sleep on the floor and i will eat
on a leaf
until i defeat the invasions
so that's the public promise he made and
that's the promise that he kept
so he devoted his entire life to
fighting off these hernik invasions and
he succeeded in defeating them
he succeeded in keeping india free of
the invaders so he's one of the great
heroes of india one of the great
emperors and our textbooks don't mention
him
so that's the thing right that's the
thing about our indian historians they
don't want to
uh
they don't want to give credit to the
great heroes of india because it makes
uh their it it goes against their agenda
their agenda is to portray india as a
nation of losers a nation that has
always lost
military wars that is always lost to
invaders and the truth
is something very different so they
conveniently keep these episodes of
history out of our textbooks so yes
our emperor sanskandagupta is one of the
great heroes of
our history
and we need
to recognize heroes such as him
okay this is a good question by goku
the japanese have been for following
dharma for centuries then why did they
commit barbaric atrocities which is
clearly not dharma against the chinese
and the koreans during their imperialist
regime very good question
i had also said in the past that uh
there's a reason why asian empires
have never have never been expansionist
and they have never been
they have never been extractive
like the european colonizers see what
the european colonizers did in africa
they destroyed africa extracted all the
world out of africa and impoverished
africa see what they did to india before
the british came to india india's gdp
was more than one third of the entire
world's gdp by the time the british left
india's gdp was less than two percent of
the world's gdp and india's life
expectancy was less than 30. that's what
they did to india they destroyed india
totally in all ways and they extracted
all the wealth out of india now asian
emperors
ching is khan for instance
and various other emperors they have
also
gone to war they have also made forged
vast empires and yet they never
indulged in the kind of practices the
europeans indulge in they never
impoverished
any conquered territory the cholas
conquered the entirety of southeast asia
but they enriched southeast asia they
did not impress southeast asia they did
not extract all the wealth out of this
area and so on and so forth
and similarly the japanese have also
been following dharma for almost nearly
2000 years at least 1500 years
and yet
you are right they committed horrific
atrocities in china in korea in the
first half of the 20th century why is it
so despite following
dharmic culture why did they do this
that is the question
you to understand why they did this you
have to go back a century
go back to the second half of the
19th century
the meiji restoration so the meiji
emperor of japan decided to totally
transform japanese society by
westernizing japanese society he tried
his best to stamp out buddhism from
japan
he portrayed buddhism as a foreign
religion as a foreign culture he did his
best to destroy buddhism and he failed
but he was able he succeeded in
creating this idea
this perception in japan that buddhism
is
a separate foreign religion
so today
japan recognizes two native religions
shinto and buddhism they are now seen as
separate before the meiji restoration
they were seen as the same thing because
they were so because
temples
in japan
uh they they followed both practices it
was very well syncretized
they had shinto practices as well as
buddhist practices now it's been
separated so that is one thing that came
out of the meiji restoration and the
major restoration aimed to
secularize and westernize japan to stamp
out buddhism and so on so the aim of the
emperor was to was to turn japan into a
non-dharmic society
he failed to do that when it comes to
the people of japan but he did
turn his entire state apparatus into a
non-dharmic apparatus
the army the bureaucracy the governance
system all that became completely
non-dharmic
it tried to imitate the west
and the consequences are very clearly
visible
in the kind of brutality
and atrocities they perpetrated on the
people of china and of korea which can
never ever
be allowed or contemplated in if if the
system was a dharmic system it it just
won't happen if the system was a dharmic
system it's so so the reason for these
barbaric atrocities was the non dharma
the determinification
of the japanese state apparatus of the
japanese armed forces see before see
what they did was that they
they uh destroyed the samurais
they massacred and killed most of the
samurai samurais were the original
warriors and warlords of japan
they were all buddhists they had a very
clear code of conduct called bushido
bushido bushido is the japanese dharmic
way of the samurai it is a buddhist
samurai code of conduct in which it is
very clear what you can do and what you
simply cannot do and honor is the
highest thing
in bushido
so that so they eradicated bushido
and they brought in a western code of
conduct western
principles western morality and that is
why japan went to the way of hell
in during the first and second world war
uh era
during the time i mean what they did in
nanjing is horrific you can't i mean
it's horrific absolutely horrific that
the kind of atrocities they perpetrated
in in nanjing and in korea
i mean
just unspeakable what they did so it's
all because they abandoned the path of
dharma that's why they did this japan
today is
to still to a large extent the dharmic
country the people follow buddhism and
shinto
of course there is a great deal of
christianization that's happened during
the us as a consequence of the u.s
occupation of japan which still
continues
but it is still very much
a dharmic society so i don't see that
ever happening again as long as the
society remains true to its culture
so i hope that answers the question very
good question
purushottam says what is the origin of
the gurkha people are they related to
guru gorakh i think i spoke about this
uh in the preview one of the previous
episodes
the uh see the origin of the gorkha
people again it's not very well
documented by historians but what i've
heard the the legendary
it's not mythical it's legendary
legendaries
the difference between
legend and history is that legends
are recollections oral records of
history
whose textual evidence has been
destroyed
it means that it actually most likely
all happened but we currently don't have
the
uh
written evidence for it so the legend
goes as
it goes like this that there was this
great warrior
baba ravel
about a thousand years ago
a great rajput warrior
who fought the turkic invaders of india
defeated them
and and expelled them from western india
from the punjab region present-day
pakistan
he established the city which is now
known as rawalpindi
and
his his guru was this the great
guru guru nanak baba gurugnath
so after he succeeded in defeating the
turks and expelling them from western
india
he went back to his guru with his
followers with the soldiers and the guru
said now we should all go and settle
down in northern india near the
himalayas
so they went northwards and they settled
down in the foothills of the himalayas
present-day nepal
right
and there they intermarried with the
local people and their descendants are
today's gorkhas
they are called gorkhas because they are
the followers of baba guruknath
so that is the legend about the origin
of the gorkhas they are
the descendants of the rajputs and of
the local people
of the himalayan foothills of india
so that's why they are great warriors
they still have this great martial
tradition they are one of some of the
best warriors you will find on the face
of the planet
and they serve in the indian army and
they also serve sadly in the british
army where they are treated like
second-class citizens
so that is the origin of the gorkhas
they're great warriors that they're the
descendants of the rajputs
who protected india and of the local
people of the himalayan foothills great
warriors
and great sons and daughters of india of
indian culture and indian civilization
so that's what i can say but
it would be nice if historians were to
actually document this properly
akshat asks in the military what do you
think is more important
submarines aircraft nuclear weapons
hypersonic defense system
alliances geopolitical alliances like
nato auk us
intelligence technology and personnel or
what you know what akshat all of this is
important
everything
has its own specific place
in the big
context of national security
you do need to say submarines i think
india a nation with a coastline as large
as india
needs 10 times more submarines than i
would say 10 times we currently have
about 12 13 functional submarines i
would say that india needs at least
80 90 maybe 100 submarines to properly
defend and administer the indian ocean
region india needs those many submarines
aircraft yes aircraft are valuable you
you
i think submarines are currently more
valuable than aircraft carriers aircraft
carriers are a big liability in my
opinion
submarines are way more dangerous but
it's always nice to have if you can
afford it one or two aircraft carriers
aircraft do
act as force multipliers
so aircraft have a certain role to play
an important role to play you need
aircraft such as
anti-submarine warfare aircraft those
poseidon aircraft
uh you need fighter aircraft
you need helicopters and so on and so
forth
reconnaissance aircraft drones etc so
various kinds of aircraft play a variety
of rules nuclear weapons are overall
good they are overall very important to
india's national security hypersonic
defense system is a totally different
story
it is not about the naval domain but in
the the overall
terrestrial domain of national security
you do need alliances
the better the stronger your alliances
the more secure you are
so yes nato a uk us all that
intelligence is extremely important so
that you know
what's happening so that you can predict
things before they happen
you need various kinds of intelligence
osint sig int and so on so forth you
need satellites in space that can
monitor your
the the the regions that are of your
interest
you need cyber technology various other
technologies you need a strong
strong uh army
personnel and so on so all of this is
important all of it has
a certain
critical role to play
in
national security national defense and
offense as well
i mean security is about defense as well
as offense
so all of this is important but when it
comes to maritime security certain
things become more important when it
comes to space security
other things become important rocket
launches missiles satellites remote
sensing uh
technology all that becomes important
when it comes to the terrestrial domain
your tanks become important your your
infrastructure becomes important
and so on and so forth
so all of it is important you need a
strong air force as well not just for
defensive operations but for offensive
operations as well
so currently we have what 28 squadrons
of aircraft which is woefully inadequate
for
our requirements
so typically they say you need 36
quadrants but if your aircraft are
capable enough there if they are foreign
4.5 generation aircraft
or fourth generation aircraft then you
can make do with less aircraft and so on
the some defense analysts will say that
the the converse also applies even if
you have second generation or third
generation aircraft
if you have a thousand of those well you
can take a take on any threat
so quality matters quantity also matters
quantity is very important quantity has
a quality of its own
so we need all of these things it's a
very complicated very complex
geopolitical environment
but all of these
factors that you have outlined in the
question they're all very important
india cannot afford
to take any of these
lightly
okay let's take some more questions
japan asks how to be an astronomer or
astrophysicist or cosmologist
how much time will it consume
well it all depends you know if you want
the official degrees then you have to go
through the entire grind of the
education system you need a college
degree a bachelor's degree in in in
science
probably with physics as
your main subject
then you need to go into
your university level level courses you
need to acquire a master's degree in in
any discipline in physics
hopefully in astronomy astrophysics
cosmology if any indian any indian
university actually gives these degrees
typically it's in
nuclear physics or or something else
electronics electronics is portrayed as
physics nowadays in indian universities
and so on so
if you want to acquire a degree you will
have to go through the entire grind of
the education system but if you actually
want to learn these things you can do
everything on your own provided you
understand mathematics provided you have
a good grasp of mathematics you can
learn these subjects
at least astronomy in two three years
doing self-study you can buy
certain standard books and there are
lots of online
courses as well entire online lectures
from mit and
cornell etc
so you can go through these lectures
very high quality lectures i think even
indian universities like iits etc have
online lectures nowadays which are
available for free
nptel courses and so on so you can
actually
if you're interested
gain all the knowledge for free online
you may have to buy a few textbooks
which are reasonably cheap and you can
actually
acquire the knowledge
necessary for doing the research in
astronomy
in maybe 2-3 years if you have this
sufficient mathematical background when
it comes to astrophysics and cosmology
it's much harder
because the mathematics is much more
involved it's much more advanced
mathematics you need a much stronger
foundation in physics in addition to
mathematics to do astrophysics and
cosmology you will need to see for
astronomy it's just about observing
observing the stars
and the various
celestial phenomena
so
for that you don't need really need to
understand electromagnetism and cause
and
quantum mechanics and relativity and all
that but in the case of astrophysics you
you need
the knowledge of these
of these fields
you will need to understand
electrodynamics electromagnetism you
will need to understand
solid-state physics you need to
understand quantum mechanics quantum
field theory
and general relativity as well in
addition to some other things
so it's much harder to become an
astrophysicist or a cosmologist
cosmology whatever you call it
astronomy is much easier so it depends
on what you want to do
so that's a very general answer
it depends on where you stand what your
mathematical
background is and whether you have
studied physics
yes or no up to which level it all
depends on that
okay let's take more questions
okay clash cloud says what was the
renaissance era in europe
so the renaissance era in europe was the
period of time about 500 or 600 years
ago
starting around that time when europe
became very prosperous
material prosperity and because of this
material prosperity there was a great
deal of investment in the arts and all
that
it all began i believe in italy in the
florentine and other regions
and you had all these great artists like
michelangelo leonardo da vinci
rafael the nutella and all these guys
who produced all this great art and it
led to a flowering of the arts and
culture
music
classical music and so on
and all that so it was all triggered off
by this period of great financial
prosperity
in europe
so that was the renaissance era so if
you want a renaissance renaissance in
any culture
the initial starting condition the
non-negotiable condition is that you
need to become financially economically
very prosperous when the entire society
is economically prosperous and stable
that's when they are able to dedicate a
great deal of time and effort energy all
that
into
the arts and all these things you know
if your society is poor you will never
have a renaissance
so that in very brief is the renaissance
era in europe
about 500 600 years ago is when it
started
and the uh
flowering of this era the greatest
period of this era was about
500 400 or 300 years ago i think i
haven't studied in great detail but
that's the rough time period in which it
happened
and that's when you had all this great
art all these great structure sculptures
the great paintings and all this great
classical architecture
that emerged in europe so that's the
renaissance era
okay let's take some more questions
harsh gen says why doesn't the
archaeological survey of india work
efficiently see the asi is is something
that the british started
the archaeological survey of india was
was
established by the british occupiers of
india the british raj
in the 19th century i believe
and
the purpose of the asi was to
uncover to some extent the history of
india to find all the interesting
archaeological artifacts
and one of the most important
tasks the asi performed was to
was to help the british steal india's
treasures
so you will find if you go to the
western countries the london museum etc
you will find
incredible amounts of priceless indian
treasures arts sculpture
sculptures and so on
all housed in that museum and you will
find the this this thing
everywhere throughout the west the
metropolitan museum in new york and
various other museums
lots of private collections and all so
much of india's ancient heritage has
been stolen in this manner
much of it happened during the british
occupation of india and the asi was very
much part of it
so it's a colonial institution after
india's independence we had some good
even great archaeologists in the asi
like like professor bibi lal et cetera
but overall it is an organization that's
run by bureaucrats who are not
archaeologists these people have no
understanding of archaeology or history
they are simply bureaucrats and they run
the asi
and it is run in a typical bureaucratic
fashion complete neglect of india's
history they don't care about the
heritage
even today there are so many monuments
that come under the protection of the
asi officially from which everything is
being stolen
even today there is this great trade
that's happening this great export of
indian treasures this great plunder and
loot of indian heritage that is still
happening as of today
under the nose of the asi
i have a video on this channel in which
i've documented i've demonstrated
that
priceless artifacts from
the harappan era of india's history are
being sold online on in
on online auction sites now a
significant portion of this is being
stolen from pakistan
but
some of it is being stolen from india as
well
and you you can see reports in india's
media in in the various news outlets
which show that you know
these archaeological sites like
and uh
virana etc they have been plundered
openly by various elements even though
they are officially under the
jurisdiction and protection of the asi
it's all because of the complete apathy
and neglect of the people who run the
asi
these bureaucratic minded people they
just don't care and the focus of the asi
is in restoring and preserving mughal
monuments and british era monuments you
go to mumbai the city of mumbai you have
all these
sites all these places like the british
colonial architecture
and the art deco buildings etc that are
preserved and protected by the asia
but you will find other places that
should be under the protection that are
completely neglected
and
the taj mahal comes under the asi in the
red fort and
fatah sikhri and so on these places are
very well protected and restoration work
is done but
india's true heritage see the mughal
monuments the british era monuments are
not our heritage
they are not the heritage of india
they are what the foreign occupiers and
oppressors of india constructed with
indian money with indian labor
but it was done according to their
culture and their tastes it does not
represent the true heritage of india the
true heritage of india is not
uh
important for the asi
and that's what we see all the time all
the time there are thousands of examples
of this
so the reason the main reason for the
for why the asi doesn't do its work
properly is first of all it's run by
bureaucrats who just don't care about
india's culture they're all mentally
colonized secondly the purpose of the
asi is is
the origin of the asi is colonial in
nature and it is very much still a
colonial
institution
it just seeks to protect and preserve
mughal and british era monuments
so these are some of the factors why the
asi is so useless
i would say that we need to disband the
asi
and create a new
professional
organization of professional
archaeologists
an organization that actually
works
towards preserving the true heritage of
india so the asi needs to be disbanded
disbanded and scrapped but obviously the
government won't do that so
so we are stuck with it
as of now
okay
mahan says my history teacher taught us
that even in the vedic culture beef was
served on rare and very special
occasions is there any truth
some scholars
have interpreted some ancient texts as
saying that on extremely rare occasions
cattle could sometimes very rarely be
slaughtered
as a sacrifice as
an offering to the gods some scholars
have interpreted some texts as meaning
that way
uh we still don't have a complete
consensus consensus on this
so i truly because i haven't studied
these these portions of the texts myself
so i cannot give you first hand yes or
no answers
but i am aware of certain scholars who
have made these claims
so if your history teacher
is aware of these claims and if if he or
she believes these claims
then they would have
taught this to you
i'm not sure if even if the if if
any cattle was slaughtered i'm not sure
if they would actually be consumed
by by people
so it is still something that is a
matter of controversy a matter of debate
the question is not settled some people
have made this claim
but i personally
am not in a position to answer this
because it is still
something that has not been settled
conclusively right
but even if something like this happened
on very rare occasions
it is just an exception it's not a
practice right
so we know as a fact that uh
cow slaughter is a great sin in indian
culture for thousands of years and the
consumption of beef is considered to be
the worst of sins
in indian culture for thousands of years
so that is the overall fact that we are
aware of
so these outliers and
these rare data points are not really
that important even if
this were to be true right so so that's
the answer
all right some more questions
okay this is by somnath abhishek
agriculture what's your opinion of on
the modernization of our farming
practices in our country
how can technology help to increase our
output and help boost or production
very good question
i think more than half of the population
of the country of india even today in
the 21st century is uh is engaged
in agriculture
i think that
most of these people do it because they
have no other option
everybody wants to
study
and go to go to a big city where there
are more opportunities
and have a more prosperous life
everybody wants that every farmer
wants their kids to go out of
agriculture
because you know agriculture is
if you have half of the country more
than half the country
engaged in an occupation that accounts
for only about five percent of the gdp
there's clearly a big problem here
so if something accounts for only five
roughly five percent of india's gdp then
i would say that only five percent of
india's population should be engaged in
that in that
occupation
and we can free up the rest of the
population
to do more productive work right
according to whatever aptitudes and
interests they have
so yes it is very important for us to
modernize
agriculture
bring in modern 21st century technology
in agriculture in the farming practices
big machinery etc so that you can
have fewer people engaged in agriculture
and there is more output the problem is
that there are not enough opportunities
today in india
in various sectors in the private sector
in the government sector there are not
enough jobs that are being created there
is not enough manufacturing
being done in india that can absorb all
this surplus
population that is currently engaged in
agriculture
when the opportunities become available
people will go out of agriculture and
start doing the work
what happened we have to look at the
history of this you know
so what the british did in india is they
destroyed india's
indigenous industries india was the
world's original first
fully industrialized civilization
from the harappan times itself india was
a fully industrialized civilization we
had in the indigenous industries in in
in metal works
in in
in the textiles
in various other sectors and so on in
shipbuilding
in
gunpowder manufacturer in arms and
ammunition in so many other things
the british destroyed india's indigenous
industries and for enforced
the majority of india's population into
subsistence farming
and that's why today as a consequence
over half the population of india
is still engaged in agriculture
their ancestors were forced into it
their livelihoods were destroyed by the
british and they were forced into
subsistence farming
and that is the root of india's
impoverishment actually
so india needs to
over time in the next couple of decades
ensure that we create enough
opportunities for jobs in the country so
that so that people can move out of
agriculture which they are doing because
they have no other choice and start
getting
involved in much more productive work
and then we can bring in modern
technology into agriculture so that
maybe five percent of the people of
india
can deal with the entire agriculture
sector so that's something that needs to
happen
it will
greatly free up
the
unleash
the actual true potential of the people
of india if this can be done
so it's a very good question
this is another very interesting
question adarsh asks
what prevents a military coup from
happening in any democratic country
do you see it ever happening in india in
the next 20 to 30 years military coup
so that's a very interesting question
and i don't see a military coup
happening in india
in the next 20 to 30 years or in the
next 50 years
i don't see it happening
there is this very interesting very
interesting book
called kudeta
by
edward luthwak
let me see if i can open this up
let me let me try and share the screen
and show you this book
one second
just a second
right so this is a book by edward
luthwak
it's called kudita a practical handbook
now this book was published in 1968 and
it showed step by step how governments
can be overthrown
it's like a manual
for uh
executing and implementing
a kudeta right
in this book edward luthor has
written about the conditions that need
to be in place
for a coup to succeed and he has also
shown
what kind of
society
is not conducive to a coup ever
succeeding
and uh so i'll not go into the details
but what he says is that if
you need to have a home a a
homogeneous kind of society
just one
ethnic group and one culture one
religion
if you have that sort of society then
who can succeed
if you have a very diverse multi-ethnic
multicultural pluralistic society
a true democratic society
then a coup can never succeed it's
impossible for a crew to succeed in the
in such a society
and india is such a society
india can be well construed to be a
multi-ethnic multicultural very diverse
very pluralistic
society with lots of different centers
of power the federal structure of india
and so on
so that is why aku can never succeed in
india india is not a mono culture it is
not a single ethnicity
because you see in india everybody sees
themselves as a separate tamil said that
we are separate from north indians
uh the bengal is said that we are not we
are very different from the odiaz the
ods will say we are very different from
the people of andhra the people of
andhra will say that we are very very
different from gujaratis the gujaratis
will serve we are very different from
the punjabis and so on and so forth
everybody has their own
ethnic group imagined ethnic group
imagined culture
and there are so many linguistic
differences
differences in uh
in traditions
and so on and so forth in practices and
so on so it's a very very very diverse
society
and in a society like that a coup can
never ever succeed
conversely if you have a country in
which you have a single religion
then a coup can succeed that's why
pakistan is always
ruled by the military even though it is
nominally a democracy
and that is also why
china is susceptible to a military coup
because china is ruled as a mono culture
just one culture which is the culture of
the chinese communist party and the
official state religion is a theism
atheism itself is a religion you know in
a way
so china
is a monoculture there is only one
dominant ethnic group the han chinese
everybody else is marginalized
in a society like china
a coup can certainly succeed and that's
why the chinese emperors like
the current president mr xi jinping
they're always paranoid
about being overthrown
so that's why china is a very
militaristic
dictatorial
country
so that's what prevents a military
kuruku from happening democracy is not
important
it can happen even in a democratic
country if it is a single ethnic group
if the country has a single ethnic group
in a single culture or religion in that
case it can happen even in a democratic
country but even in a country that is
not a democracy if it is a pluralistic
country a coup can never succeed and so
on and so forth you know
so very very interesting question i
would recommend that if if you can get
your hands on the book
kudita by by edward luthwalk then
then you should try and read it it's a
very interesting book
should we change our education system to
how it used to be in ancient india
i um
i would say that we certainly need to
change
the education system we need to
transform it radically we need to reform
it greatly but it can we can never bring
it back to the state it was in ancient
india because ancient india was a
thousand years ago before the invasions
turkic invasions it was a very different
culture very different society
it was a very different time
the population was much much lesser than
what it is today in india so the entire
context has changed today what we can do
is we can draw inspiration from the best
practices that were in place
a thousand years ago
and we can try and implement something
similar to that but in the 21st century
context with 21st century means and 21st
century methods
we need to look forward
but be inspired by what happened in the
past
we cannot try to go back to
the state we were in a thousand years
ago it's simply impossible we have to
embrace the 21st century we have to
embrace
embrace everything that is there today
we have always been a culture that has
been at the forefront of science and
technology so we have to embrace 21st
century science and technology
and
use that
to take our education system
forward
so that is what needs to happen there
are a number of things that can be done
to truly transform the education system
but one would need the government to
show some willingness
for that
we currently
are not have not yet reached that stage
right right right let's take some more
questions many of the questions i see
i have already answered those questions
so i will not take those
let's take this question ishwar roshan
says
china claims that they have ruled tibet
for 800 years in the past
yeah the chinese communist party claims
that their emperors
ruled tibet
and that is they according to them what
gives their
uh
occupation of tibet legitimacy
historical legitimacy so let us
unpack this claim that the chinese
communist party continually communicates
to the world that our emperors
ruled tibet and that's why we
are the legitimate rulers of tibet
first of all tibet is a different
different ethnicity it's a different
culture the tibetan language has nothing
to do with the chinese language
the tibetan people are a different
ethnic group they're not chinese they're
not han chinese
the tibetan culture is totally different
from chinese culture tibet is part of
the indo-sphere
tibetan culture is a very interesting
and very beautiful local manifestation
of indian culture
buddhism vajrayana buddhism tibetan
buddhism is a very specific local
manifestation of indian culture of
dharma with tibetan characteristics
right
so there is nothing in common between
the han chinese and the tibetans nothing
in common
now they claim that their emperors rule
tibet and that's why tibet is a
conquered country conquered people and
that's what the chinese communist party
has the right to rule tibet that's the
claim so let's understand what is the
basis of this claim
the basis of this claim
is the
assertion by the chinese communist party
that the chinese yuan dynasty
ruled tibet
okay so let's understand what actually
happened during this time what was the
yuan dynasty
the chinese yuan dynasty that ruled from
beijing
what was this yuan dynasty
the first
actual emperor of the yuan dynasty
ethnicity
he was
mongol
both his parents were mongols what was
his mother tongue
it was the mongol language what was his
culture
it was
buddhism his religion was buddhism his
ancestral culture religion was tengrism
again that is non-chinese his
grandfather was the greatest conqueror
of all time chinggishkhan
who conquered china and smashed china
he flattened the city of beijing
right
so the yuan dynasty
was a mongol dynasty that conquered
china and they ruled as conquerors
it was a conquest dynasty
it was not a chinese dynasty
and in their historiography the first
emperor of china was actually
chingaskhan not kublai
and the second emperor of china was
ogodakhan and the third was kublai khan
so this was a mongol dynasty that
conquered china and ruled china as
foreign occupiers
now what is the relationship between the
mongol yuan dynasty and the tibetans
it was a guru shishya relationship
a teacher-student relationship kublai
khan
declared well they don't declare
officially but he made buddhism the
state religion the state culture
okay so that's what it did and
the mongols of obviously did not have a
great deal of understanding of buddhism
so he employed tibetan
gurus
as the official
gurus of the empire
of of buddhism of the empire
so
the yuan dynasty
took tibet as a protectorate they
pledged their protection to tibet they
did not invade tibet ever
they did not occupy tibet ever with
their soldiers
they simply extended their official
protection to tibet as a protectorate
mongol soldiers
passed through tibet on many occasions
when the great ching is khan when the
great shri ching is khan
went westwards to destroy the
empire of the turks he went through
tibet
he did not stop in tibet he did not
destroy tibet he did not touch the
tibetan people he just passed through
tibet
went to iran and central asia destroyed
everything there in retaliation for
their atrocities and then he came back
to mongolia again through tibet again he
did not
stop in tibet or conquer tibet or occupy
tibet he just went back
so the mongolians never conquered but
they never occupied tibet they extended
their protection to tibet and they
treated the tibetans as their gurus
so it was a guru shisha relationship a
teacher-student relationship
tibet was not a client state or a
conquered kingdom
it was a protectorate
so
the claim that the
chinese yuan dynasty conquered tibet and
ruled tibet is false it is a lie first
of all the yuan dynasty was not chinese
and secondly they did not ever conquer
or rule tibet
so that is the lie that the chinese
communist party is using to justify
their illegal illegitimate and brutal
occupation
of tibet
that's the answer sir
okay let's take some more questions
prakriti varma asks if religions like
jainism and buddhism were started after
the demise of their last
tirthankar
respectively
then how do we know that there were
gurus even before them
okay prakriti so first thing i would
like to say is that jainism
and buddhism
and hinduism
are not religions
there is only one
there is no religion in india really
there are only three religions which are
the abrahamic religions
uh
judaism
is the oldest
then christianity and then islam
these are the three religions
and the western world tries to portray
all other cultures and traditions as
religions
the definition of a religion is this
it has a single god
a single prophet
and a single holy book
that is the definition of a religion
when it comes to
jaina dharma about the dharma or
sanatana dharma there are hundreds if
not thousands
of sacred texts
there are no prophets
and there is a multitude of gods
and divinities
divinity
in dharma lies in all of us all of us
have a spark of divinity in us
divinity permeates the entire universe
everything is a manifestation of
divinity there are gods everywhere there
is there are gods and trees gods and
animals gods and your guests
and gods everything everywhere so jaina
dharma about the dharma
hinduism what you call hinduism today
these are not religions this is the
ancient ancestral culture
of india and of the entire indo-european
world
of the past
it was all wiped out from europe by the
advent of christianity
it was wiped out by force by brutality
and the only place where this ancient
culture persists is india
so that is about religions so jainism
buddhism the case of hinduism are not
four different religions it is just the
same
it's the same tradition these are
different manifestations the different
schools of thought different uh
schools of philosophical thought of the
same ancient tradition and culture
now
jainism did not begin with the demise of
vardham and mahavir the last tirthankar
according to jaina tradition their
tradition is as old as dharma itself
their tradition is dharma itself
what we call hinduism or buddhism
and they have had in a very
long lineage
of tirthankars who came before vardaman
mahavir
i think vardaman mahavir was
if i am not mistaken the 24th tirthankar
i think so if i'm mistaken i apologize
but i think he was the 24th tirthankar
according to jaina tradition so the
other question is why do we should we
believe this
this is the ancient tradition of the
jaina dharma and why should we not
believe it
and similarly
in both the dharma
siddhartha gautam
was simply the last known buddha there
were many buddhas before him
and there will be buddhas again who will
emerge in the future
so it's a very long lineage of buddhas
and great gurus
great spiritual leaders it is something
that is going to continue
in the future
so that is the context in which
uh
we should look at
these uh matters
so these are not religions
right and they did not start after the
demise of their last tirthankara buddha
these are living traditions that are
very very ancient
they are as ancient as dharma itself
they are as ancient as
india
and the indian people itself
we don't even know
when indian culture first emerged
because we have this archaeological
record that goes back at least 10 000
years in the indian subcontinent
and there is clear evidence of cultural
continuity for this ten thousand years
so we had the same culture
it was not some different culture
earlier we have the same culture
and i would say that
jaina dharma dharma etc they're all part
of the same tradition right it is now
today construed and interpreted by our
academics and historians as four
different religions which is just lies
it is
it is uh they're trying to force fit
western
concepts on indian
traditions it doesn't work like that
but unfortunately this is what we're
taught today and this is how everybody
sees
indian culture we now see indian culture
our own culture through western eyes
that is called mental colonization we
have to
get over this we have to decolonize
our minds we have to unlearn the
nonsense we have been taught and we have
to relearn our history
in whatever way we best can
so good question prakriti i hope that
answers the question
rumble tv asks why are canada and the us
best friends forever bff
uh there is this uh
there is this
alliance
official alliance called the five
eyes
alliance
five eyes
that is the us
the uk
canada
australia
and new zealand these five countries
have an official alliance
in which they share all their
intelligence
and they share and they have this
military cooperation very close
military cooperation and so on these
five countries these are the five
anglo-saxon dominate countries the five
english-speaking countries
so they trust each other more than they
trust any other country
so the the reason why they are bff best
friends forever is that because they
have the same origins they have the same
culture the same language
they are all the result the product of
british
colonialism
british invaders
invaded and occupied north america
they destroyed the native culture in the
native people it was a horrific genocide
the native americans were wiped out very
few of them remain and they are today
even today they live
very uh
they are still deeply marginalized even
today they are second-class citizens in
america in the us and also in canada
so the british occupiers colonizers
colonized the whole of north america
which is now the us and canada they also
colonized australia
did the same kind of genocide there
and today it is the country of australia
similarly in new zealand also they to a
large extent wiped out the natives and
the culture the maoris still exist in
new zealand they are also second-class
citizens there
the maori culture is being eroded and
wiped out today from new zealand
and so on so these are all
um
countries
that are the result the product of
british colonization and genocide of the
natives
right
so they all originate from
england and that's why they're all best
friends forever that's why they have
this very close-knit cooperation among
each other they have the same origins
they have very similar histories and
they are all ruled by people who are not
native
to the land
so
that explains why they are best friends
forever
dungar singh johan asks why did buddha
and mahavira question the authority of
the vedas if these were part of hinduism
okay
see there is no such thing as hinduism
there is something called dharma dharma
and both the dharma and the jaina dharma
are part of
overall
dharma these are dharmic schools of
thought philosophical school of thought
i have explained this multiple times in
the past you can check out my older
videos about this indian philosophy in
which you have nine systems of indian
philosophy uh charvaka jaina both
vedanta
uh yoga sankhya
and so on so forth right nine of these
some of these schools of thought can be
construed to be atheistic schools of
thought
in which they do not recognize
the existence of any divinity any
creator god
for instance charvaka does not recognize
any
it is a purely materialistic school of
thought there is no god there is no
karma there is no nothing
but it is also part of sanatana dharma
similarly
in
jaina dharma for instance there is no
concept of god
but it does recognize the existence of
the soul every human being has an
eternal soul every animal has an eternal
soul every
particle
has a certain
amount of soul in it even trees of souls
but the consciousness levels are less
and jaina dharma also recognizes the law
of karma
but it does not recognize the existence
of any god
but all the characteristics are still
very much dharmic
it does emphasize nonviolence and so on
so it's very much part of dharma
similarly both the dharma
does not recognize the existence of any
god but it does recognize the existence
of the soul atma now you will be taught
by your teachers and by history
textbooks
that according to both the dharma the
soul is not permanent
the soul also is temporary which is a
lie
and
your teachers in your history textbooks
will teach you that both the dharma
does not recognize the authority of the
vedas
that is again
a lie
what i would encourage you to do
is to read
the lord buddha's death bed discourse
the mahaparinirvana discourse
the last public discourse that he gave
the night before he died
in the mahaparinirvana discourse
he has specifically clarified
that he taught certain things because
people were very immature they could not
understand things in their entirety but
in the last discourse
he clearly stated
that the atma is permanent it is not
temporary
and he also stated that the vedas are
the supreme authority
mahapray nirvana discourse read it it's
available online
i think it's very strange that all these
scholars even buddhist scholars
try to portray both the dharma as
something that does not recognize the
vedas
and it reckon it treats the soul as a
temporary thing
i don't understand what is the agenda in
trying to
sideline
the last discourse of lord buddha of
gotham buddha
in the city of kushinagar the night
before he died he gave this public
discourse
and in that in that discourse he has
clearly recognized the authority of the
vedas
and the permanence of the atma
so it very much brings buddhism under
the
umbrella of dharma
in the in the in
in jaina dharma i
think the existence of god is denied of
god or god is denied atma is there
karma is there and it also questions the
authority of the vedas that's why jaina
dharma is considered to be a gnostic
school of thought
so nasty is not something that denies
the existence of god but it is something
that questions the authority of the
vedas so according to that definition
jaina dharma is a gnostic school of
thought but it still does come under
the overall
framework of sanatana
dharma
so i hope that answers your question
dungar it's a very good question many
people have this question i have
answered it to some extent in the past
but i am glad that you gave me the
opportunity
to clarify
this matter good
right let's take a couple more questions
aditya says why do people give credit of
freedom to mohandas gandhi when more
than seven lakhs people were martyred
for our freedom we don't even know how
many people died for our freedom
we had so many uh rebellions against the
british occupation that are simply
erased from history
all the records have been wiped out they
are not mentioned in our textbooks there
have been many local
uprisings against the british that were
crushed brutally
many massacres happened
in 1946 there was a massacre in the city
of mumbai there was a massacre in the
city of karachi
hundreds if not thousands of people were
shot
on the streets
the way people were shot in the 1989
tiananmen square massacre but do our
historians speak about this no they
don't speak about this it happened just
one year before the transfer of power in
1947.
people were shot to death hundreds of
people on the streets of mumbai on the
streets of karachi
and our great historians do not write
about this and our great mahatma
mr gandhi did not say a word against
this
so this is the problem our historians
our school textbooks
our politicians our leaders
they all make a public display of
worshiping mohandas gandhi and that's
why people
believe them
if you are taught from the age of three
that we owe our freedom
to mr mohandas gandhi you're gonna
believe it it's not your fault you don't
you believe this right
i don't blame the people of india
they have been misinformed from the time
they were born
from the time they went to school on the
first day
and this misinformation continues even
after you leave the education system the
media keeps
portraying gandhi as a mahatma
the movies keep doing that the
politicians keep doing that he's even
there on on the currency notes in india
so it is not the fault of the people of
india that they believe that gandhi is
the reason why we got our freedom we
still haven't got our freedom we are
still a colonized country
and as long as we keep worshiping
mohandas gandhi we're going to stay
colonized
so
so many people millions of people tens
of lakhs of people have given their
lives and their blood for the freedom of
the country
and they have all been erased from
history and everything is now
attributed to the fake mahatma mohandas
gandhi so this needs to change and i'm
glad that people at least here in this
little group
i'm glad that people are now beginning
to realize what the truth is they are
beginning to realize
that we have been lied to all these
decades
and i think this is going to only
intensify and more and more people will
start knowing the truth in the coming
years it needs to happen it will happen
and only then with the force of all
these people will india be able to
gain its true freedom from the colonial
mindset
okay let's take
one more question
let's take one more question
let's take a couple of more questions
other asks since supersymmetric
particles are not found
what do you think is next after the
standard model in particle physics
what's the future of particle physics
okay that's a very good question so the
context is this uh
there is this theory called
supersymmetry
in which uh it it says it predicts that
you will find
supersymmetric particles partners
of the standard model particles
so the standard model particles are the
uh
the 16 17 particles right the
bosons the fermions
uh the the hadrons the force carriers
and so on so forth and you will have
supersymmetric particles partners of
these particles and it was hoped that
the large hadron collide of the lhc
it would be able to provide evidence
of the existence of these particles but
no such evidence has been forthcoming
and therefore the theory of
supersymmetry is more or less dead
and therefore it is a big failure the
only new particle that the lhc was able
to discover was the last piece of the
puzzle the missing boson
which is the higgs boson
that's the only particle that was
discovered nothing else has come out of
the
experiments that have been done for
years in the lhc no new particle has
been discovered no super symmetric
particle and therefore the so the theory
of super symmetry
is i would say in my opinion it is dead
dead and cold right so what is next
after the standard model in the particle
in particle physics what is next is dark
matter this enormous mystery of dark
matter so there are two enormous
mysteries in cosmology one is dark
matter the other is dark energy dark
matter is about 20 21 approximately
roughly
of the matter of the universe dark
energy is more than 70 percent of the
mat of the mass energy composition of
the universe so dark energies could
perhaps be a force of some kind
it is clearly most likely not a some
kind of particle
so it is a an even deeper mystery but
dark matter is most likely some kind of
particle that interacts only
gravitationally so that is the next
frontier in particle physics to
try and uncover the true nature of dark
matter
what sort of particle is it is it's a
single particle is it a class of
particles is it a family of particles
does it have something to do with
primordial black holes microscopic black
holes is it something else entirely we
still don't know and that is the next
frontier in particle physics we will
have to understand gravity the force of
gravity
more deeply than we currently do
to be able to crack this mystery the
21st century is supposed to be was was
supposed to be the century of
gravitation we are almost more than
one-fifth of the way into the century we
have made no progress whatsoever so
things are going to have to change in
physics
the current environment of group think
and this entire string theory mafia that
has taken over
theoretical physics it will need to be
overcome and
overthrown
if we are to make progress in
in theoretical physics in particle
physics and if we are going to move
forward in our understanding of the
universe
so good question
okay let's take one more question
why do the turkish people look european
because their ancestors
were europeans
at least their female ancestors were
europeans if you get my drift
okay so that the turkish people their
ancestry more than 90 of the genetics
would be the local genetics
of the
mediterranean region the anatolian
region their ancestors were the greeks
the armenians
and so on there is very little turkic
ancestry in these people
but the culture is the old turkic
culture the language is the turkic
language
and i am sure that they are patrilinear
lineages are turkic lineages
so that's why they look european because
they are european by blood by ethnicity
all right
what shall we do now
shall we
shall we take some more questions
one more question perhaps
dungar singh johann says why do we add
ism in hinduism in what way does this
deteriorate our culture
first of all this term hindu
is
an exonym it is a name that is given by
foreigners to
to india and india's culture
the parsis the persians who are our
brothers actually who are the
descendants of our ancestors the parsees
they called the sindhu river the hindu
river because in in the in the old
persian language
the s was replaced by h
so sindhu was called hindu and so on so
forth saraswati was called
so they called the sindhu river the
indus river sindhu they called it hindu
and later this entire region was called
hindu or hind and then this name was
given to the people of india
and when the turks invaded india and
conquered india
parts of india they called the local
people hindus
because of the iranian
name for this region
and then the british also started doing
that and then later on even the indians
started calling themselves hindus
and then this
foreign ism was placed at the end of
hindu so it became hinduism so these are
all foreign concepts foreign terms which
we have internalized and absorbed it is
called mental colonization
so the correct word for our culture is
dharma it is not hindu it is not
hinduism or any of that nonsense it is
simply dharma
if we understand that then we will be
able to decolonize so yes this term
hinduism and this this adjective hindu
it actually denigrates and
in a way like you say deteriorates our
culture it it perpetuates the mental
colonization that is prevalent
throughout our country even i use the
term hinduism all the time
so i am equally guilty you know
in in continuing this that's just the
way it is right now
so good question
okay okay i think uh it's one minute 41
hour 45 minutes i'm gonna stop it here
so great great session people thank you
very much for your questions we will
continue this in the next session
the next session is not tomorrow it is
on monday tomorrow is a special day many
of you have requested me not to do it
tomorrow because there's a qriket match
india pakistan
so enjoy the match tomorrow we will have
the session on monday it's going to be a
video chat session
so i will see you then until that time
take care
thank you and i will see you soon
all right